<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reformation, or, The duty of magistrate and people a sermon preach'd before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor and aldermen in the parish church of St. Lawrence-Jewry on the feast of St. Michael, 1697 at the election of the Lord Mayor for the year ensuing / by Richard Lucas ...</title>
            <author>Lucas, Richard, 1648-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B26321</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17164997</idno>
  <idno type="VID">206335</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264219332</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3413</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">17164997</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B26321)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 206335)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1619:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reformation, or, The duty of magistrate and people a sermon preach'd before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor and aldermen in the parish church of St. Lawrence-Jewry on the feast of St. Michael, 1697 at the election of the Lord Mayor for the year ensuing / by Richard Lucas ...</title>
                  <author>Lucas, Richard, 1648-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Sam. Smith and Benj. Walford ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="uniform_title">Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CXIV, 16 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:206335:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:206335:1"/>
            <p>Dr. <hi>LƲCAS</hi>'s SERMON PREACHED At St. LAWRENCE'S Church on <hi>Michaelmas-Day</hi> last, Before the Lord Mayor, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="order_to_print">
            <pb facs="tcp:206335:2"/>
            <head>Clarke Mayor, Jovis <hi>Septimo die</hi> Octob' 1697. <hi>Annoque Regis</hi> Willielmi <hi>Tertij</hi> Angliae, <hi>&amp;c. Nono.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THIS Court doth desire Dr. <hi>Lucas</hi> to print his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon preach'd at St. <hi>Lawrence</hi>'s Church on <hi>Michaelmas-Day</hi> last before the Lord Mayor, Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Citizens of this City.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>GOODFELLOW.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:206335:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Reformation: Or the Duty of Magistrate and People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd before The RIGHT HONOURABLE THE Lord Mayor AND ALDERMEN, IN THE Parish Church of St. <hi>Lawrence-Jewry,</hi> on the Feast of St. <hi>Michael,</hi> 1697. at the Election of the Lord Mayor for the Year Ensuing.</p>
            <p>By <hi>RICHARD LƲCAS,</hi> D.D. Vicar of St. <hi>Stephen</hi>'s <hi>Coleman-street.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>Sam. Smith,</hi> and <hi>Benj. Walford,</hi> at the Princes Arms in <hi>St. Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. 1697.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:206335:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:206335:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PSALM CXIV. 16.</hi> Who will rise up <hi>for me</hi> against the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil-doers? or who will stand up <hi>for me</hi> against the Workers of Iniquity?</head>
            <p>THIS <hi>Psalm</hi> is variously expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Some suppose that the <hi>Church</hi> does here complain of the Perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of <hi>Idolatrous Nations,</hi> and implore the Aid of God and Man against them; but whoever reflects on the 7th and 8th <hi>Verses,</hi> will easily see, that by <hi>Evil-doers</hi> and <hi>Workers of Iniquity</hi> in my Text, the <hi>Psal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mist</hi> does not mean the <hi>Heathen</hi> and <hi>Infidel,</hi> but Atheistical and Impious <hi>Israelites.</hi> Others consider <hi>David</hi> in this <hi>Psalm</hi> as a <hi>private</hi> Person, and in distress; and think that in the words of my Text he begs the Defence and Protection of <hi>Man,</hi> as in the beginning of the <hi>Psalm</hi> he had done that of <hi>God,</hi> against his implacable and too powerful Enemies: but whoever will look more closely into the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign of this <hi>Psalm,</hi> will soon see, that <hi>David</hi> here is not acted by <hi>Fear</hi> but <hi>Zeal;</hi> that 'tis
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:206335:4"/>not his <hi>own Enemies,</hi> but the <hi>Enemies of God and Goodness</hi> he sets himself against: Nor is it his <hi>own Defence,</hi> but the <hi>Overthrow of Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edness</hi> which he aims at. I think therefore we ought to look upon <hi>David</hi> here in a <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> Capacity, as a <hi>Prince</hi> or <hi>Magistrate;</hi> and then as such he deplores the Increase and Confidence of the Wicked: and having for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify'd himself in God by Prayer, he resolves, in the words of my Text, to do the Duty of his Station, to imploy all the power God had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him for the Extirpation of Wickedness, and the Reformation of an impious People, and earnestly invites and calls in to his Assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance all that had either Heart or Ability for such a Work, as being well aware of the great difficulty of it. <hi>Who will rise up</hi> for me <hi>against the Evil-doers? or who will stand up</hi> for me <hi>against the Workers of Iniquity?</hi> This is the Sence I prefer, not only for the Reasons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alledg'd, but also because it best becomes the Zeal and Faith of <hi>David,</hi> best suits the Spirit and Genius of several other parallel <hi>Psalms,</hi> and seems plainly to me to have the Countenance of the <hi>Targum</hi> and <hi>Septuagint.</hi> In the words thus explain'd we have these <hi>three</hi> things:</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:206335:4"/>1. <hi>The deplorable State</hi> of <hi>Israel.</hi> This is easily to be collected from the form and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of <hi>David</hi>'s expressing himself here, <hi>Who will stand up for me? who will take my part?</hi> As if he should have said, Such is the number and power of the Wicked, that how much so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever my heart is set upon a Reformation, I can hardly hope to effect it, without the Concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and joint Endeavours of good Men. And yet alas! how little is the Assistance I can reasonably expect of this kind? How few are the sincere Friends of Goodness? How great and general is the Coldness and Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence which possesses men in the things of God?</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Duty</hi> of the <hi>Magistrate.</hi> This is plainly imply'd here, and is, to curb and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strain Wickedness, and to promote a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Reformation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Duty</hi> of all <hi>good People.</hi> Which is, as far as in them lyes, to assist and encourage the Magistrate in this good Work. I begin with the <hi>first</hi> of these:</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>deplorable State</hi> of <hi>Israel.</hi> The <hi>Psal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mist</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:206335:5"/>does not here reckon up all the Sins which then polluted the Land; but only ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serves to what <hi>height</hi> Wickedness was grown. Impudence and Atheism, or something equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volent to it, and Crimes of no common size now reign'd and rag'd every where. <hi>Sin</hi> was no longer the <hi>work of darkness:</hi> Transgressors were above the fear both of Shame and Laws: they had thrown off all Reverence for the <hi>God of Jacob,</hi> and hop'd in a little time to see all others do so too. Though they were such as were not to be endur'd in any Community, yet were they so far spread, and had so ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd themselves into places of Power and Profit, that they were in a Condition to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press the Godly, and to project the utter Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpation of Vertue, and the Eastablishment of Wickedness in its room, by their Influence and Authority. All this is plainly to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd from the <hi>Psalmist</hi>'s <hi>Description</hi> of those times: <hi>Lord, how long shall the wicked, how long shall the wicked triumph? How long shall they utter and speak hard things, and all the workers of iniquity boast themselves? They break in pieces thy people, O Lord, and afflict thine he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritage. They slay the widow and stranger, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:206335:5"/>murder the fatherless. Yet they say, The Lord shall not see, neither shall the God of</hi> Jacob <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard it.</hi> And <hi>v.</hi> 20. <hi>Shall the Throne of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity have fellowship with Thee, which frameth Mischief by a Law?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was indeed a <hi>miserable,</hi> a <hi>desperate</hi> state of things: and yet we have reason to fear that our <hi>own</hi> is as bad; nay, considering the Means and Motives we <hi>have</hi> enjoy'd, and still <hi>do,</hi> worse. Our Wickedness, both in <hi>practice</hi> and <hi>principle,</hi> is at last arriv'd at the utmost <hi>maturity</hi> it is capable of. It is not <hi>luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmness</hi> in <hi>practice,</hi> 'tis not too great a <hi>lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude</hi> in the <hi>Faith,</hi> 'tis not <hi>Disputes</hi> about <hi>things indifferent</hi> that we now complain of, but downright <hi>Apostacy</hi> and <hi>Infidelity.</hi> The utter Subversion of all Religion is now threatned by <hi>Atheism</hi> and <hi>Deism,</hi> by Clubs and Combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of Wretches, who believe either <hi>no God</hi> at all, or none but <hi>such</hi> a one whose Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Attributes <hi>consist</hi> well enough with the worst of <hi>Vices.</hi> Order and Decency, Peace and Unity, Church Discipline and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are things that we have <hi>long ago</hi> accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stom'd our selves to contemn and slight: but <hi>now</hi> we are come to treat the <hi>Gospel</hi> it
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:206335:6"/>self as a <hi>cunningly devised Fable,</hi> and <hi>Vertue</hi> and a <hi>publick Spirit</hi> as things that none have an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Esteem for but <hi>Fools</hi> and <hi>Superstitious.</hi> Now when these are our <hi>Principles,</hi> when these are openly abetted and industriously spread in Publick and Private, in Print and Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation, to the reproach of <hi>Christianity,</hi> and the scandal and shame of <hi>Magistracy</hi> and <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> what <hi>Morals</hi> are we to expect amongst us? what, but just such as we find? We were <hi>long ago</hi> Lewd and Carnal, Factious and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious, Admirers of the Pomp and Osten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Life. But these are the common and usual Vices of Prosperity in every Age: we have <hi>now</hi> advanc'd much further. We are False, and Base and Cowardly, Corrupt and Perfidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. There is no Truth, no Justice, no In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity amongst us: much less any Love of our Country, or Zeal for any thing that is commendable or lovely. <hi>Before</hi> we were se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd by Prosperity against Conscience: but there was yet hope, because something of Conscience remain'd: but <hi>now</hi> alas! Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is look'd upon as a Notion fit only to awe and scare the Weak and Simple. <hi>Before,</hi> we were too far estrang'd from that <hi>Purity</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:206335:6"/>and <hi>Peaceableness,</hi> which are the inseparable Properties of <hi>heavenly wisdom:</hi> but <hi>now</hi> we are as far estrang'd from <hi>common Honesty</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi> without which, I will not say <hi>Religion,</hi> but even <hi>Human Society</hi> and <hi>Trade</hi> cannot subsist. These are the glorious Fruits of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theism</hi> and <hi>Deism,</hi> and I know not what late <hi>Discoveries</hi> and <hi>Innovations</hi> in <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Politicks.</hi> And all this is but the <hi>natural</hi> course of things; for <hi>ill Principles</hi> do as naturally breed <hi>Immorality,</hi> as <hi>Immorality</hi> does <hi>Ruine;</hi> according to that of the <hi>Psalmist, The Fool hath said in his heart there is no God;</hi> and then it follows, <hi>They are corrupt, they have done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable works, there is none that doeth good.</hi> Psal. 14.1.</p>
            <p>This now is our <hi>state:</hi> how <hi>dangerous,</hi> how <hi>deplorable</hi> a one, no Man can be insensible, who is in any degree thoughtful and serious. And where is it now we are to seek for <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dress?</hi> To whom are we to apply our selves for <hi>Reformation?</hi> Shall we despair, Shall we quit the design of it, and, forbearing all at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of our own, leave the Work wholly to God? If so, we need not doubt but God will one day or other assert his Truth, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:206335:7"/>vindicate his Honour; but it will be in our <hi>Ruine,</hi> not <hi>Reformation.</hi> For when God has <hi>try'd</hi> us long under the richest means of Grace, the fructifying Influences of his Word, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, and Spirit, and we bring forth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>Briars and Thorns;</hi> when he has <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercis'd</hi> us long under the various Discipline of Judgment and Mercy, and we bring forth nothing but Fraud and Falshood, Violence and Oppression; what are we to expect from God, but that he shou'd accomplish upon <hi>us</hi> all the <hi>Woes</hi> denounc'd against <hi>Jerusalem</hi> in the like case, <hi>Isai.</hi> 5. and sum'd up <hi>v.</hi> 5, 6? <hi>And now go to, I will tell you what I will do to my Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard: I will take away the hedge thereof, and it shall be eaten up; and break down the wall thereof, and it shall be trodden down. And I will lay it waste, it shall not be pruned, nor dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, but there shall come up briars and thorns. I will also command the Clouds that they rain no rain upon it.</hi> I doubt not but you will be of opinion with me, that we ought to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent this Sentence by some Endeavours of our own for <hi>Reformation.</hi> To <hi>whom</hi> then shall we <hi>address</hi> our selves? To the <hi>Masters of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies?</hi> 'Tis true, they <hi>can</hi> do <hi>much,</hi> and <hi>much</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:206335:7"/>one day will be <hi>requir'd</hi> of 'em. But alas! when the <hi>day</hi> has been spent in <hi>cares</hi> and <hi>drudgery,</hi> the <hi>evening</hi> is commonly spent in <hi>mirth,</hi> or <hi>wine,</hi> or <hi>worse:</hi> so that little, I doubt, is to be expected from hence. Shall we then fix our hopes upon <hi>Religious Societies,</hi> confederated and enter'd into for this very purpose? I am glad, I confess, to see a <hi>Spirit of Religion</hi> stir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and moving <hi>any where</hi> amongst us; and I know not how far <hi>this leaven</hi> may go towards the fermenting the <hi>whole lump:</hi> But alas! <hi>They</hi> do not possess all those <hi>Advantages</hi> which are necessary for so great a work. Shall we then expect Reformation from the <hi>Clergy?</hi> God, I confess, has set them as <hi>Shepherds</hi> and <hi>Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> over his Flock, and it cannot be deny'd but we may and ought to do much <hi>more</hi> than we do; I pray God make us sensible of the great <hi>account</hi> we are one day to render of our <hi>Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardship.</hi> But alas! you cannot be ignorant, that <hi>this</hi> is one of the crying Sins we <hi>complain</hi> of, that the great Endeavours of this Age are to render the <hi>Ministry</hi> of this Body of Men <hi>use<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less</hi> and <hi>unserviceable;</hi> by malicious slanders and other ill methods to extinguish all Reverence for their Persons and Office; and by pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:206335:8"/>Errors to defeat the power and efficacy of their Doctrine: Nor can you be ignorant how far these have succeeded. From <hi>whom</hi> then are we to expect a <hi>Reformation?</hi> From the <hi>King?</hi> He indeed is invested with <hi>power</hi> enough, and <hi>God has done great things</hi> for him. I hope he is truly sensible of it, and has it upon his heart to make the best returns he can. Especially since our <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Liberty,</hi> without <hi>this,</hi> are far from being <hi>secur'd,</hi> our <hi>Deliverance</hi> far from being <hi>compleated:</hi> and whatever <hi>honour</hi> he has <hi>himself</hi> acquir'd either by <hi>War,</hi> or by <hi>this Peace,</hi> it will want its greatest Beauty and Perfection; nay, I fear, be utterly blasted, if it be not ripen'd and consummated by the <hi>Glory</hi> of a <hi>Reformation.</hi> But after all, will not he be ready justly to take up the <hi>words</hi> of the <hi>King of Isreal</hi> in my Text, and in the sence I have given of them, <hi>Who will rise up</hi> for me <hi>against the wicked?</hi> &amp;c. The <hi>Burthen</hi> is <hi>too great</hi> for <hi>one</hi> alone, were he great as <hi>Moses</hi> himself: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is the <hi>Civil Power communicated</hi> in lesser Streams and Branches, from the <hi>Root,</hi> from the <hi>Fountain,</hi> from the <hi>Supream Magistrate,</hi> to <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate</hi> ones. On <hi>you</hi> then is devolv'd a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty part of this Duty. From <hi>you</hi> therefore, the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:206335:8"/>
               <hi>Magistrates of this City,</hi> we are to expect stre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous and zealous Attempts for a <hi>Reformation.</hi> The eyes of all good Men may be reasonably upon <hi>you.</hi> The <hi>station</hi> you hold, the <hi>power</hi> you participate, lay great <hi>Obligations</hi> upon you, and give you great <hi>Opportunities.</hi> From you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> and the <hi>People</hi> may justly <hi>demand</hi> and <hi>expect</hi> very great Advances in the <hi>work of Reformation.</hi> All this will more fully appear from my <hi>second General;</hi> which is,</p>
            <p n="2">II. The <hi>Duty</hi> of the <hi>Magistrate.</hi> That this is to curb and quel the Ungodly, and cut off wickedness from the Cities of our God, will be plain to any one that shall consider the End of Civil Power, and the Influence of Vertue. If we enquire <hi>why</hi> God has put the Sword into the hand of the Civil Magistrate, <hi>why</hi> the Supream, Universal Monarch of Heaven and Earth has communicated a Ray of his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to Man, <hi>Scripture</hi> and <hi>Reason</hi> will soon inform us. St. <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 13. after he has asser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Origin of <hi>Civil Power</hi> to be <hi>from God,</hi> and from thence inferr'd the <hi>Obligation</hi> of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriors to <hi>Obedience, not only for wrath, but also for Conscience sake;</hi> he does at large <hi>describe</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:206335:9"/>the Office of a Magistrate, consisting in what I have laid down, <hi>v.</hi> 3, 4, 5. St. <hi>Peter</hi> advances the very same Doctrine, only a little more compendiously, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13, 14. <hi>Submit your selves to every Ordinance of Man for the Lord's sake; whether it be to the King as Supream, or unto Governours, as unto them that are sent by him, for the punishment of Evil-doers, and for the praise of them that do well.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we consult <hi>Reason,</hi> this will soon tell us, that <hi>that</hi> is truly the great <hi>End</hi> of <hi>Civil Power,</hi> which when <hi>attain'd,</hi> the <hi>Community</hi> arrives at the greatest <hi>happiness</hi> it is capable of, and without which all other Advantages are either useless or pernicious. And this is certainly <hi>Religion:</hi> This is the Spring of all wise Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels and Conduct, and of all handsome and worthy Actions. This inspires the <hi>Magistrate</hi> with Wisdom, Integrity and Zeal for publick Good. This produces Obedience in the <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> towards their Prince, and Charity towards one another. This begets and nourishes Sobri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety and Courage in the <hi>Souldier,</hi> and Truth and Justice in the <hi>Trader.</hi> This is, in a word, the only solid Foundation of a People's strength and glory: for it gives us Peace and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:206335:9"/>Unity, and Wealth at home, and Reputation abroad. But on the other hand, as <hi>Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness exalts a Nation,</hi> so <hi>Sin is the reproach of any People.</hi> This blasts all our Secular Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, and defeats all the hopes the most pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mising Circumstances can raise in us. <hi>Wealth</hi> without Religion does but invite <hi>Invasions,</hi> and render us a richer Prey. The strength and skill of <hi>Arms</hi> without Religion, naturally tends to <hi>Tyranny</hi> or Civil <hi>Tumults:</hi> or if a <hi>Martial</hi> Genius and Power be wisely or luckily <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted</hi> on <hi>foreign Wars,</hi> this in effect is but to <hi>oppress our selves</hi> in order to <hi>infect others.</hi> As to <hi>Peace, there is no peace, saith my God, unto the wicked.</hi> This is as true with respect to the Peace of <hi>Publick Societies,</hi> as to the Calm and Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility of a <hi>private</hi> Bosom. Without Religion, Selfishness &amp; Sensuality, Lust, Passion &amp; Fancy, must be the predominant Principles in us; and these are restless and humorous, dividing, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious and weakening ones. They naturally <hi>embroil</hi> us with neighbouring Nations, or with one another, and make us at once <hi>unfit for war,</hi> and <hi>incapable of peace.</hi> In one word, were Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion exterminated, and Wickedness substi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted in its room, without <hi>any other</hi> Evil or
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:206335:10"/>Enemy to attack us, we should unavoidably <hi>sink</hi> and <hi>perish</hi> under the weight and persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our <hi>own Vices.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet, after all this, I have made you but a very <hi>imperfect</hi> Representation of the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Influence of Religion and Wickedness. I must put you in mind <hi>further,</hi> that there is a <hi>God,</hi> a God <hi>who judgeth and ruleth the Earth;</hi> that the <hi>Sins</hi> of any <hi>Nation</hi> do certainly sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject it to <hi>his wrath</hi> and <hi>displeasure,</hi> and their <hi>Vertues</hi> entitle it to <hi>his favour</hi> and <hi>protection.</hi> What the <hi>Prophet</hi> publisht to <hi>Judah,</hi> is in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the standing <hi>Rule</hi> of the <hi>Divine Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> over <hi>all Nations. If ye be willing and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, ye shall eat the good of the Land: But if you refuse and rebel, ye shall be devoured with the Sword; for the Mouth of the Lord hath spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken it.</hi> Isai. 1.19, 20. And the <hi>following</hi> words are so <hi>applicable</hi> to <hi>us,</hi> that they may justly fill us with <hi>Melancholy</hi> apprehensions. <hi>How is the faithful City become an Harlot? It was full of Judgment, Righteousness lodged in it, but now Murderers. Thy silver is become dross, thy wine is mixt with water. Thy Princes are rebellious and companions of Thieves: every one loveth gifts, and followeth after rewards. They judge
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:206335:10"/>not the fatherless, neither doth the cause of the widow come unto them. Therefore saith the Lord, the Lord of Hosts, the mighty one of</hi> Israel, <hi>Ah! I will ease me of mine Adversaries, and avenge me of mine Enemies.</hi> Nor let us flatter our selves with <hi>Security,</hi> because God hath <hi>sheath'd</hi> the <hi>Sword</hi> by an undeserved <hi>Peace.</hi> Unless we repent and reform, he can soon <hi>draw</hi> it again, and turn the <hi>point</hi> upon our more <hi>sensible</hi> and <hi>vital parts:</hi> or if he don't do this, he wants no Artillery, no Instruments of Vengeance; he needs but restrain the Influences of Heaven, or let loose the Elements upon us, and we shall soon perish by Deluges or Conflagrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by Earthquakes, Plagues, or Famines.</p>
            <p>Thus I have plainly <hi>prov'd</hi> the <hi>Proposition</hi> laid down, that the great Business and Duty of the Civil Magistrate is, to maintain and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance Righteousness, and to cut off and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpate Ungodliness. For I have shew'd that this is the great End for which God confers Power and Authority upon him: that <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness</hi> and <hi>Wickedness</hi> have necessarily a mighty Influence upon the Prosperity or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sery of every Community: and lastly, that the Favour of God is the necessary Consequence
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:206335:11"/>of the <hi>one,</hi> and his Displeasure of the <hi>other:</hi> And <hi>this alone</hi> is at any time enough to make us a <hi>happy</hi> or <hi>unhappy Nation.</hi> The <hi>Result</hi> of all is briefly this, the <hi>good of the Pepole</hi> is the great <hi>Concern</hi> of the <hi>Magistrate;</hi> and therefore it is <hi>as plain,</hi> that 'tis the <hi>Duty</hi> of the <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate</hi> to endeavour <hi>at this time</hi> a <hi>Reformation,</hi> as it is that the <hi>good of the People depends</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it. From this <hi>Doctrine</hi> thus clear'd will follow these two or three plain <hi>Inferences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Now that we see the <hi>Duty</hi> of the <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate,</hi> 'tis easie to infer <hi>what</hi> kind of <hi>Men</hi> are <hi>qualify'd</hi> to be <hi>Magistrates,</hi> namely such as <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thro</hi> recommended to <hi>Moses,</hi> Exod. 18.21. <hi>Able men, fearing God, men of truth, and hating co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetousness. Able men;</hi> Men of Rank and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, Men of a great and just Reputation and Interest, founded on known and solid Vertues. <hi>Fearing God;</hi> this is the foundation of all Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Vertue; 'Tis impossible that <hi>such</hi> shou'd be either Enemies to Wickedness, or hearty Friends to Righteousness, <hi>whose Minds</hi> are not possess'd with a due and awful sence of God. <hi>Men of truth;</hi> i. e. of Uprightness and Integrity; that cannot be wrapt by Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:206335:11"/>or Ambition, nor influenced by Friends or Parties, by any selfish fears or hopes: but will readily pursue their Duty in defiance of all worldly Considerations to the contrary. <hi>Hating Covetousness;</hi> Selfishness is a flat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction to a Publick Spirit, and 'tis impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that the Sordid and Covetous shou'd ever be capable of any thing so great and lovely as Religion and Honour. <hi>These</hi> are the <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters</hi> which <hi>fit</hi> Men for the <hi>Chair; these</hi> are the <hi>Men</hi> whose <hi>Example</hi> will derive <hi>Force</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> on their <hi>Zeal for Reformation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. From hence 'tis plain that they who choose such Men for Magistates as are not qualify'd for it, betray the trust which God and the Government have repos'd in 'em: That they are in effect Enemies to their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and their Country; and the Grounds they proceed upon, whatever they be, can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be wise nor good. The great and excellent <hi>Ends</hi> of <hi>God</hi> can never be serv'd by <hi>ill Men;</hi> by Men whose <hi>Practices obstruct</hi> that Vertue which their <hi>Power</hi> should <hi>promote,</hi> and are so far from being an <hi>Ornament</hi> to their Station, that they are a <hi>Dishonour</hi> to it, and serve on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to bring <hi>Magistracy</hi> it self into <hi>contempt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:206335:12"/>3dly and lastly, Since <hi>Magistrates</hi> are the <hi>Ministers of God,</hi> and the great End of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is to restrain Vice and propagate Vertue, 'tis plain that they must at the last day render an <hi>account</hi> of their Office <hi>to God,</hi> and stand or fall as they have answer'd or disappointed this Expectation of God. It will not <hi>then</hi> be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider'd what <hi>expence</hi> they have made, what <hi>part</hi> or <hi>figure</hi> they have maintain'd, or what <hi>party</hi> they adher'd to; but how heartily they have sought the <hi>good of the people</hi> committed to their charge: which is, in other words, how zealously they have persecuted wickedness, and espous'd the interest of Religion. The <hi>Psalmist</hi> therefore puts <hi>Magistrates</hi> in mind, that <hi>God</hi> heedfully <hi>superintends</hi> and <hi>observes</hi> their <hi>deportment,</hi> in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to <hi>judge</hi> 'em. <hi>God standeth in the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the mighty: he judgeth among the Gods.</hi> Psal. 82. And by laying before 'em the vast <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance</hi> of <hi>Magistracy</hi> to the <hi>World,</hi> for 'tis the <hi>support</hi> of it, he suggests to 'em how great, how dreadful a <hi>punishment</hi> must be justly due to <hi>negligence</hi> or <hi>corruption</hi> in it. <hi>They know not, neither will they understand; they walk on in darkness: all the foundations of the Earth are out of course,</hi> v. 5. And at last, lest they should flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:206335:12"/>themselves that their <hi>power</hi> and <hi>greatness</hi> can <hi>shelter</hi> and <hi>skreen</hi> them from Vengeance; he puts 'em in mind that they are <hi>mortal,</hi> and can no more escape <hi>judgment</hi> than they can death: <hi>I have said ye are Gods, and all of you are Children of the most High; but ye shall die like Men, and fall like one of the Princes,</hi> v 6, 7. And as <hi>it is appointed</hi> for <hi>Rulers</hi> as well as <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate</hi> Men <hi>once to die,</hi> so consequently to <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in judgment.</hi> And what a <hi>dreadful account</hi> will he have to give at the <hi>last Audit,</hi> who has been selfish or sottish? who has prostituted his power to gratifie some vile Lust or Passion, and betray'd the honour and interest of Justice and Vertue to serve some By-end?</p>
            <p>To prevent this sad issue of things, give me leave to lay before you the <hi>Example</hi> of an <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Governour,</hi> which I would earnestly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire you to follow in proportion to your En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments and Power; it is that of <hi>David</hi> in <hi>Psal.</hi> 101. He there proposes to himself three things, and I do not doubt but he did steadily pursue 'em throughout his Reign. 1. He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solves upon the <hi>practise</hi> of the strictest <hi>vertue</hi> in his <hi>own person;</hi> without which he well knew he cou'd not expect the propitious Presence of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:206335:13"/>God with him, either to guide or bless him. <hi>I will behave my self wisely in a perfect way; O when wilt thou come unto me? I will walk with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in my house with a perfect heart. I will set no wicked thing before mine eyes: I hate the work of them that turn aside, it shall not cleave to me,</hi> v. 2, 3. Next he resolves to <hi>purge</hi> his <hi>Court</hi> of all wicked and ungodly Men, and to <hi>plant</hi> it with such as <hi>fear God:</hi> to cashire the peevish and ambitious, the treacherous and fraudulent, the factious and contentious; and to receive into his friendship and service Men of Truth and Integrity, Lovers of <hi>Religion</hi> and their <hi>Country;</hi> and therefore sure to be <hi>faithful</hi> to <hi>both. A froward heart shall depart from me, I will not know a wicked person. Whoso privily slandereth his neighbour, him will I cut off: him that hath an high look and a proud heart will not I suffer. Mine eyes shall be upon the faithful of the Land, that they may dwell with me;</hi> and so on. Lastly he resolves to put the <hi>Laws</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all notorious Offenders in vigorous <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution</hi> And the truth is, the <hi>Civil Laws</hi> of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses</hi> are full and severe enough against all wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and scandalous Crimes, and needed not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Arbitrary Power</hi> to supply their defects: So
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:206335:13"/>that the <hi>Psalmist</hi> might very well express this his sence in the manner he does; <hi>I will early destroy all the wicked of the Land, that I may cut off all wicked doers from the City of the Lord,</hi> v. 8. O bright example! O wise and holy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutions! <hi>Happy</hi> will <hi>this Land</hi> be, when God <hi>shall</hi> vouchsafe to raise up such a Spirit as this in <hi>our Prince,</hi> and in <hi>all that are put in Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity under him.</hi> Certainly all that have any se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious thoughts about <hi>Religion</hi> and the Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of it, must earnestly desire to see <hi>that day,</hi> and make it the daily subject of their importunate Prayers. Which minds me of my <hi>third</hi> and <hi>last Head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. The <hi>Duty</hi> of all <hi>good People,</hi> to <hi>serve</hi> and <hi>assist</hi> the <hi>Magistrate</hi> in his Endeavours for <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation.</hi> Which is here call'd, <hi>The standing up with him against the workers of iniquity.</hi> I need not surely prove this to be our Duty. We cannot save <hi>our own</hi> Souls without doing what God has put in our power towards the saving those of <hi>others:</hi> without this we must not pretend to <hi>Religion.</hi> For what a strange sort of Religion is that which has neither <hi>Zeal for God,</hi> nor <hi>Charity for Man?</hi> and <hi>he</hi> can
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:206335:14"/>be suppos'd to have but very <hi>little of either,</hi> who will not contribute what he can to the maintenance and propagation of Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and the suppressing Wickedness. It often happens, and it is a deplorable face of things when it does so, that the great, and the rich, Men of place and power, are the Fautors and Abettors of Sin; not only doing ill themselves, but delighting in those that do so. It often happens that Vice has gain'd that Ascendant and Authority in a Nation (unhappy the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion where it has!) that it defies, not only all the Exhortations and Denunciations of the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> but the Force and Majesty of <hi>Laws</hi> too. In this case, not <hi>subordinate Magistrates</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but even <hi>Princes</hi> themselves will need the counsel, the industry, the help and service of others; and shall <hi>we</hi> be accounted the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God and Lovers of Vertue, if we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press no concern or zeal for <hi>either</hi> upon such an occasion?</p>
            <p>If it be said, we do not dispute our <hi>Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation</hi> to do what we can in such a Cause as this is; but what is it that we <hi>can</hi> do? I answer, I do not doubt but that frequent <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities</hi> will offer themselves, when you
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:206335:14"/>may seasonably testifie your good will to it. But besides <hi>these,</hi> there are some <hi>general</hi> ways of doing it, to which we are all equally tyed. Such are, for instance, a cheerful Obedience to the Magistrate, a fair and candid constru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of his Conduct, a just honour and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steem for him on the account of what he does well, fervent and constant Prayers to God for a Blessing upon him, that he may be endow'd with a <hi>Spirit of Wisdom and Counsel,</hi> of Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and Constancy, and may be ever under the protection and guidance of God. Nay, there is something <hi>more</hi> then all this that we <hi>can</hi> do; we may <hi>reform our selves,</hi> we may employ much care about <hi>our Families,</hi> we may count enance and encourage the <hi>Publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship,</hi> by our constant Attendance upon it, and an equal and reverent Deportment at it, and we may, in all <hi>Conversations,</hi> signifie our <hi>dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like</hi> of every thing that has any tincture of <hi>Impiety.</hi> By this means we shall make the work of the <hi>Magistrate</hi> very easie, we shall strengthen his Hands, and confirm him in his just Resolutions; and we shall give check to the confidence of Sinners, and Sin will again sneak and hide it self in Dens and Darkness,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:206335:15"/>when it meets with that open and honest opposition which it ought, from all that make profession of Christianity. Do you yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire <hi>more particular</hi> Directions? consider <hi>by what Arts ill Men</hi> endeavour to propagate <hi>Wickedness,</hi> and from hence you will soon see how you are to <hi>obviate</hi> and <hi>countermine</hi> 'em. Are <hi>they</hi> industrious to advance ill Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and to subvert Primitive Christianity? <hi>we</hi> must <hi>contend earnestly for the Faith once delivered to the Saints,</hi> and be industrious to keep it firm upon its first grounds. Are <hi>they</hi> for <hi>cashiering</hi> Churches, Liturgies, Priests, and Sacraments? It is even from hence plain, that 'tis the Interest of Religion that <hi>we</hi> shou'd pay a just <hi>regard</hi> to 'em. Do <hi>they</hi> combine to <hi>blast</hi> and <hi>oppress</hi> by Calumnies and ill Arts all good Men, and especially those who are more peculiarly engag'd in the Defence of Religion? <hi>we</hi> must <hi>encourage, vindicate, sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port,</hi> and <hi>honour</hi> such. Do <hi>they</hi> labour to <hi>divide</hi> and <hi>embroil</hi> us? <hi>we</hi> must sincerely <hi>follow after those things that make for peace.</hi> Finally, are <hi>they</hi> zealous to <hi>promote ill Men? we</hi> must be so to <hi>set up good ones.</hi> I will now <hi>sum</hi> up all, and <hi>conclude.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:206335:15"/>
            <p>Our <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Nation</hi> are miserably corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and debauch'd; and while they are so, we can never promise our selves Prosperity or Safety. God has, 'tis true, at this time given us a <hi>Peace;</hi> 'tis another <hi>Trial,</hi> 'tis an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other <hi>Call;</hi> we, indeed, may make it a great and lasting <hi>Blessing.</hi> But alas! unless a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> follow, <hi>Peace</hi> does but skin our Wounds: we bleed inwardly, and our ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Vitals waste. What will it avail us to repair our <hi>Losses,</hi> if at the same time we pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue and multiply our <hi>Sins?</hi> What will it signifie that we are deliver'd from the Fear of a <hi>Mortal Enemy,</hi> when, on this supposal, <hi>God</hi> must still have a <hi>Controversie with our Land?</hi> A <hi>Reformation</hi> then you will all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge necessary: and certainly, if you consider what Influence the Conduct and Morals of <hi>this City</hi> have upon the <hi>whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> and what an account both <hi>Magistracy</hi> and <hi>People</hi> have one day to give of their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility to do good, you cannot but conclude that it ought to begin from <hi>hence,</hi> and to be strenuously prosecuted by the joynt Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of the Magistrates, and others of this <hi>great,</hi> and if you will do your Duty, I doubt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:206335:16"/>not but I shall soon be able to add, <hi>flourish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>happy City. Whether now you will hear, or whether you will forbear,</hi> I must <hi>leave</hi> that to <hi>you;</hi> but <hi>Heaven and Earth</hi> will one time <hi>witness</hi> that I have this day sicerely <hi>put you in mind</hi> of your <hi>Duty.</hi> If you neglect it, certainly your Prosperity and Honour will be a very little, or a very short Blaze. For are they not the words of <hi>God</hi> in a much like case? <hi>Them that honour me, I will honour; and they that despise me, shall be lightly esteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed?</hi> 1 Sam. 2.30. But alas! suppose our <hi>Temporal</hi> Prosperity should be prolong'd? what then? Is there not a <hi>day,</hi> a <hi>terrible day coming,</hi> when Parties and Passions shall be no more, when the strength of Sides and Factions shall be scatter'd and dispers'd for ever, when all the little Politicks and Subtilties of Man shall be miserably exploded and expos'd, and <hi>the Lord alone shall be exalted in that day?</hi> Then shall <hi>Electors</hi> and <hi>Elected appear before the Judgment Seat of Christ,</hi> and give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of your Trust; and then shall ye all <hi>receive according to what you have done in the Body, whether it be good or evil.</hi> Ah! <hi>Day joyful</hi> to the <hi>Righteous,</hi> but <hi>dismal</hi> to the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:206335:16"/>
               <hi>Wicked!</hi> I will add one short <hi>Remark,</hi> and I have done. The <hi>Language of the Text</hi> seems to me to be wholly <hi>Metaphorical,</hi> consisting of <hi>Military Terms:</hi> this indeed suggests to us that <hi>Reformation</hi> is a Work wherein you must expect to be <hi>encounter'd</hi> with great <hi>Opposition</hi> and many <hi>Difficulties.</hi> But let <hi>no Man's heart fail him</hi> for <hi>this:</hi> The <hi>Cause</hi> is the <hi>Lord's;</hi> and whoever engages in it, fights under the <hi>banner of God,</hi> enjoys the <hi>Prayers of good Men,</hi> the <hi>Ministry of Angels,</hi> and the <hi>Aid of the Holy Spirit;</hi> and may with a holy <hi>Assurance</hi> use the <hi>words,</hi> and expect the <hi>Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess</hi> which <hi>Moses</hi> did when the <hi>Ark</hi> set forth: <hi>Arise, O God, and let thine Enemies be scatter'd; Let them also that hate thee flee before thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:206335:17"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Several Books published by Dr.</hi> Richard Lucas, <hi>Vicar of St.</hi> Stephen<hi>'s</hi> Coleman-street, <hi>and sold by</hi> S. Smith <hi>and</hi> B. Walford <hi>at the</hi> Prince<hi>'s</hi> Arms <hi>in St.</hi> Paul<hi>'s Church-yard.</hi> 1697.</head>
            <p>DR. <hi>R. Lucas</hi>'s Practical Christianity: Or, an Account of the Holiness which the Gospel enjoyns, with Motives to it, and the Remedies it proposes against Temptations, with a Prayer concluding each distinct Duty, in <hi>Octavo. Price</hi> 3 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi> 1693.</p>
            <p>—Enquiry after Happiness, in several Parts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Vol. I. in <hi>Octavo,</hi> the third Edition, Enlarged, 1697. Price 3 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>— The true Notion of Human Life: Or, A second Part of the Enquiry after Happiness, in <hi>Octavo,</hi> third Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, 1697. Price 2 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—<hi>Religious Perfection:</hi> Or, A third Part of the Enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry after Happiness. The second Edition, Corrected, in <hi>Octavo,</hi> 1697. Price 5 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>— The Duty of Apprentices and Servants. 1. The Parents Duty how to Educate their Children, that they may be fit to be employ'd and trusted. 2. What prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is needful for such as enter into Service, with some Rules to be observed by them, how to make a wise and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Choice of a Service. 3. Their Duty in Service towards God, their Master, and themselves, with suitable Prayers to each Duty, and some Directions peculiarly to Servants, for the worthy receiving the Holy Sacrament, published for the benefit of Families, in <hi>Octavo,</hi> Price 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—Christian Thoughts for every Day of the Month, with a Prayer, wherein is represented the Nature of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned Repentance, and of perfect Love towards God, in <hi>Twelves,</hi> Price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>— The Plain Man's Guide to Heaven; containing first his Duty towards God; secondly towards his Neighbour; with proper Prayers, Meditations, and Ejaculations; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed chiefly for the Country-man, Trades-man, Labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, and such like. The second Edition, in <hi>Twelves.</hi> Pr. 1 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>— Several Sermons preach'd before the Queen, the Lord Mayor, and on other Occasions.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:206335:17"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>